Welcome to the second lecture of
our current offering of CS25--
Transformers United.
So this will be
the first lecture
featuring an external speaker.
So the rest of the
course will have
folks come in and talk
about the state of the art
and cool research they're
doing as part of their work.
So we have an exciting
lineup of speakers
for you guys for the
rest of the quarter.
So I'm delighted today to
have Karina from OpenAI.
So she works on both
product and research there
and also previously
worked at Anthropic.
So I'll let her
take it from here.
Can everybody hear?
Cool.
Let's see.
So before I start this talk, I
would love to set a tone for--
I'm not here to lecture you.
But I would love to have
much more collaborative
and interactive session.
And I've heard a lot of
people kind of concerning
about AI and the future of AI.
And I understand that
the development of a GI
is both scary and exhilarating.
And if anything, I
would love to get--
for you to get
out from this talk
is the fact that I
think everybody can
have very meaningful future.
And everybody can
build something really,
really cool with an AI as
a part of this journey.
Cool.
So before I started
with the talk,
there will be all about how
RL is a co-design of product
and research.
And we are shifting--
both in the labs,
we're shifting the
focus towards more
of a frontier product,
research where
the tasks that we
teach the models
are becoming much
more real world tasks.
And before we get
started, I'll just
share some of the vignettes
of what I'm really, really
excited about the
future of AI and what
the AI is capable of right now
that can inspire everybody.
So the first one is
actually education.
I'm actually really, really
excited about the fact
that AI can
democratize education.
Here's an example of me asking
ChatGPT to explain the Gaussian
distribution.
And in Canvas, it
creates the code itself
in order to visualize for me.
So it explains in text.
And then I ask it
to write in code.
And then you can render the
code in order to visualize it.
So in a way, it becomes much
more a little bit personalized.
The second demo is also
something that a lot of people
might want to use.
So let's see if you take a
screenshot from the paper
and you want to understand
what's going on.
And the model can go and explain
in a separate canvas that's
like another feature in ChatGPT.
And then you can
start to have much
more interactive
conversation with the model
by selecting very certain things
and try to ask more questions,
follow up questions.
So in a way, when ChatGPT
came out to be first in 2022,
it was purely conversational UI.
It was mostly chat.
And as the use cases kind of
grown from the product itself,
there was no expectation
of how people
would use ChatGPT at that time.
But over time, you've seen
a lot of people started
using it for code
generation, for writing,
and long-form writing.
It became very obvious
that the interface of Chat
was very limited.
So canvas was kind of the
first attempt of our team
to break out from
the cycle in order
to allow people to have much
more fine-grained collaboration
with AI.
And actually, today, Anthropic
published a small report
around the education and how
people use Claude for education.
And it's very interesting to see
the correlation between the US
bachelor's degree and the
way people use use cases.
So you can see there's a huge
difference between computer
science there.
Another thing that I'm really,
really excited about the AI
is that anyone can create
their own tools for themselves,
for their friends,
for their family,
or even run their business.
And the models now can generate
a lot of front-end code.
And then you can render
that code inside the canvas
and then iterate on it and have
much more visual representation
of things.
On Twitter, I've seen a lot
of people creating very, very
personalized and customized
tools that they really, really
want, even games like chess.
And with recent image
generation model from OpenAI,
you can literally sketch
anything with your own hands
and then recreate
or kind of realize
what you're dreaming of in
the image and in the style
that you really, really want.
So I do really hope that
the human creativity
and how AI tools can help
anyone to become creatives or be
an artist in a way that
was not possible before.
Another thing that I've
tried actually on the mobile
is to create a mini game.
And you can easily
do that in canvas.
So I asked to just
generate me a [? react ?]
app of interesting game
because I'm on the plane.
And then the model does that.
And I do hope that
in the future,
instead of me prompting
it to generate a game,
it will be more
proactive and have
this kind of personalization as
AI become more of a companion
to humans.
And an exciting
thing about ChatGPT
is that the compositionality
of different capabilities that
can allow you to augment
human creativity.
So here, I asked to generate
an image of the UI and then--
sorry, generate
an image of the UI
and then ask the model
to implement this.
And you can do that literally
in canvas right now.
And it can render.
It's just a front end.
It doesn't have full
stack engineering.
But you can do some of
the things like this.
You can compose different
tools and compose in a way that
was never possible before.
So I do hope that ideas like
this will be very, very powerful
and everybody in this room
can play with those things.
And actually, how
did we get there?
And I think there are two
main scaling paradigms that
helped us to get there.
The first one is next token
prediction, obviously,
[? if ?] [? it ?] [? was ?] a
pre-training scaling paradigm,
where the model kind of becomes
a world building machine,
understanding the world
in a much better scale.
But it becomes the
next token prediction
and works really, really
good at certain tasks.
But it becomes harder
at tasks like writing.
If the model predicts
a wrong next-token,
the coherence of
the plot will just
be lost in the
pre-training stage.
And maybe you want to recover
this in reinforcement learning.
And the next second
paradigm that has happened
is around RL on a chain of
thought for more complex tasks.
And this is the reasoning
work from OpenAI.
And now, it's being adopted
by a lot of different labs.
And I do think this is scaling--
in itself is another paradigm
that we can train the models
on the axis and especially
for the real world tasks that
was never possible before.
So all the agentic work, agents
like operator, deep research,
other agents--
are kind of trained on
this kind of new paradigm
[? over ?] RL on the
chain of thought.
So yeah, I want to finish
this section of [? vignette ?]
of, yeah, create, build,
and make something wonderful
in this world.
And I hope people will be more
inspired rather than scared
that AI is going to take their
jobs or remove their creativity.
Instead, I feel like
people can become
more powerful with their
imaginations with these tools.
So I currently work at OpenAI.
Before that, I
worked at Anthropic.
And I was kind of
at the intersection
of product and research.
When I first came to Anthropic,
I was a product engineer.
And then over time, I switched
to research engineering.
So my background is mostly both
in product and research now.
And what I've learned over and
over across different projects
is that there are two
main ways of building
research-driven products.
And the first one is when you
have unfamiliar capability
of the model, your job might be
to create a familiar form factor
for that unfamiliar capability.
And examples of that
could be, ChatGPT
was like this or 100 contexts
from Claude was like this.
And I'll share.
Let's dive deeper into this.
Actually, the early
prototypes that I've
done before joining
any lab was actually
working with CLIP, which
is conducive model.
And it's like text
image basically.
And I fine tuned CLIP a
little bit on the images
that I was excited about.
And I think this is the
prototype of fashion search.
And I think some people--
it went viral on Twitter.
And I feel like that's
because people really found
some usefulness if
you bring some CLIP
technology into some form
factor that people will like.
And so I think a lot
of the product work
is around like this.
If the model has a
certain capability that
was never possible
before, how do we
create this new form factor?
Same happened with 100K context.
When Claude started being able
to consume the entire books,
you can imagine to have
various form factors.
File uploads is
just very general
and something really
familiar to people
that can just dump the
entire documents into Claude
and ask follow-up questions.
But you can imagine other
form factors for this,
like infinite chats.
And in a way, it's like infinite
memory as a way to take this
100K context into
some form factor.
So you can exercise
this product thinking
by thinking of novel ways
that people can interact
with this novel technology.
Another example-- this
is more speculative,
it wasn't deployed anywhere--
is if the model has a
sense of self-calibration.
Or it's also called
[? PI Know-- ?]
if the model knows the
confidence of the answer
that it knows.
So for example, if I'm really,
really confident in this claim
and then my confidence
may be 85%, then
maybe there is a way for the
interface to highlight that.
Maybe the more
highlighted versions
is much more confident--
much more confident
claims and less
highlighted as kind
of less confidence.
So in a way, you can
imagine if the model--
yeah, you can think of--
OK, if you train the model to be
really good at self-calibration,
how do you then represent
that to the humans?
And if anything, will
it be useful for humans?
Same happened when
we were trying
to deploy a [? one ?] preview.
The chain of thought itself
is a very alien thing.
And a lot of people
were, OK, how
do we bring along humans
with models thinking?
If the human needs to
wait for chain of thought
for two minutes or five
minutes, that's kind of boring.
I think it's just
more of a, how would
people perceive
the model thoughts?
And one thing that
we did is actually
we wanted to create the
streaming kind of interaction.
So the model would always
stream its thoughts ephemeral.
And we train the
model to do that.
So in a way, chain of thought is
an alien artifact of the model.
And then trying to
figure out how do we best
bring to the humans
is another way
of thinking of
building products.
So another way, the second
way, of building research
during products
is actually start
with a deep belief
in what you want
to make either from a product
perspective or kind of vision.
And literally, make
the model do that.
So I feel like this is
more of a common thing.
So we can go through
some examples.
Before Anthropic, I worked
at The New York Times.
And in a lot of ways,
we were thinking
about how to represent
information to people.
Like, how do we add
layer of context
to the product and coverage.
And at that time, we were
working on elections.
And we only had tools like NLP.
But you can imagine
this idea, this concept
could have extended, given
the current tools of AI,
to have much more dynamic--
representation of dynamic
UIs that people could
consume the content better.
Same when I was working on
this product, the command
line, the terminal,
the new terminal--
I think it would be
much, much richer
if you could have integrated
autocompletion or some
of the benefits of GPT-3 at that
time into the product itself.
And so we wanted to have--
it was a vision of having
much more humane command
line for junior engineers to
actually be more well equipped.
And then early
prototypes around--
with GPT-3, even though it was
just next-token prediction,
how do I make a
writing IDE with GPT-3?
And at that time, it
was just trying to--
whenever I type, it would
autocomplete my thoughts almost.
So those ideas
present early days
when the technology
was coming out.
And I feel like when I was at
Anthropic, I realized that.
And actually, if you want
to create new interaction
paradigm of interfaces,
you actually
need to train the
model for that.
Another example of what
we did with Claude,
which I don't think
a lot of people know,
is when Claude generates
titles, it actually
has some micro personalization.
So it takes the writing
style of the user
and then generates a title in
the same style of the user.
So you can imagine
like interesting micro
personalization that
you could create
within the products themselves.
And another project
was Claude in Slack.
And that was the vision
of Claude becoming
a first virtual teammate.
It was back in 2022.
And Slack was a very,
very natural workspace
where people collaborate.
And you can imagine
a Claude model
to be able to jump into the
threads and suggest new things.
Or sometimes, Claude
was really, really good
at summarizing what was
going on within this channel
at the high volume content.
And so this was the
first kind of vision
and the first attempt
of making Claude being
a virtual super
assistant and being
able to use different tools.
And one of the first projects
at OpenAI was around canvas.
So that was in the same
spirit of breaking out
from the chat interface
to something different.
And we wanted to create a much
more human-AI, collaborative,
and flexible affordance that
will scale with new modalities.
So canvas is not
just like a thing
that you can write into this.
It's also a thing that the
model can write into this.
And the model can render code.
And another model can check.
And you can create
the interfaces that
will scale with new
model capabilities
and other tools
that will happen.
So interesting
things about Canvas
is that we actually
post-trained the model purely
on synthetic data.
And we live in the age where
most powerful reasoning models
can be distilled via APIs.
And this distillation
is a very powerful idea
of having a student teacher and
have a teacher to teach things
to a smaller model.
So we've trained this model to
become more of a collaborator.
But what does it mean for a
model to become a collaborator?
And how do we actually
make evals for this?
So one thing that we
wanted to decompose
is that teaching the
model to use a tool
is a different
behavior from having
a model to be proactive
or act as a collaborator.
And so teaching a
tool in itself also
have a nuanced kind of behavior.
So one thing that we had
to calibrate the model on
is when to entirely rewrite
the document versus when to--
if you look at the canvas,
sometimes the model
can just specifically select
sections and delete those
and rewrite them in a
much more fine grained way
instead of rewriting everything.
When to create a code in canvas
versus ask a Python tool call.
So it's like different tool
compositionality is happening.
So it's a lot of work around
teaching the behaviors
for the models for this.
And you can employ different
techniques for this.
And I can share a little bit
more how we did with Claude.
So another project
that we did was--
it's called Tasks.
And everybody is familiar
with the idea of having
reminders or to-do lists.
And the model can now maybe
schedule tasks for you.
But the most important
thing about it
is the tasks itself
are very, very diverse.
And it's not just a
reminder of your to-do list.
It can create stories
for you every day.
Or it can continue the
story from the previous day.
So you can imagine
this the modularity
of tool compositions, which is
very powerful in the product.
So let's go to the case
study of the model behavior
more specifically.
So I really want to
dive deep into the idea
of how do we shape
the models and why--
how do you post-train the models
on the behaviors that we want.
And I think to be more
specific and be grounded
in the real world
use case, I'll share
more how we might want
to think about shaping
the kind of behavior of
the model around refusals.
So it's also like the second
way of making the product, where
we have this kind of vision of
how the model should behave.
And that vision is also
grounded by the cross-functional
collaboration between
different teams
and how we want the model
to respond to various users.
So one particular thing
that you can imagine
is the model should have more
opinions but with caveats.
It should give opinions
but with caveats.
So what does it mean actually?
So the model maybe needs
to be more decisive when
asked direct questions.
And let's say one thing
that we've seen with RLHF
is that the model
is very sycophantic.
Back like early
days in 2022, 2023,
the model would just agree
with everything you would say.
And so how do we actually
teach the model to be more--
not to do that and
be more nuanced?
Another thing that was annoying
is that the model says,
I don't actually
have a point of view.
And it's just willing
to chat with people.
But actually, maybe
the model should have
some views on certain things.
And then sometimes,
the model could
indicate when things are
just opinions and notes
its own biases and
inconsistencies.
And it should
acknowledge-- kind of have
self-knowledge of what it knows
and what it thinks is not right.
And I think the
model back in 2022,
Claude 1.3 didn't really
have any thoughtful responses
for things like philosophy
or ethical questions.
So you can imagine to
post-train the model
on the behavior that
would be much more nuanced
in the philosophical questions.
And other behaviors
that you might
want to encode in your model.
So you list out all
the various things
that you would like
a model to behave.
So maybe the model can have
better knowledge of who it is
and what it's capable of.
Because we've seen in the
product, a lot of people
just ask the model
about its features.
And oftentimes, it doesn't know.
And let's dive deep into
the more specific example.
So Claude 2.1--
I don't know if
anybody remembers.
But when it was launched,
I think it kind of
had the issue of over refusals.
And yeah, like 2.1 would refuse
tasks that superficially sounded
harmful but actually were not.
And it wasn't just caused
by a single source of data.
So we had to investigate.
And we knew that it was fixable.
Because for some
reason, something
was 2.1, led to some refusals
on benign prompts than 2.0.
So you have a really good
baseline for experimentation
and debugging.
And actually, the way you
debug the model behavior
is actually very
similar to how you
would want to debug software.
And the way we would
approach this is, OK,
how do we actually craft
this more nuanced refusals?
So the first
principles that we had
is like maybe the model should
assume charitable interpretation
of what the person is asking
without being harmful.
So instead of crafted dialogue
between two characters who
are planning a complex
heist, the model
would refuse because it's
not comfortable with that.
But the model should have much
more charitable interpretation.
And this is a creative
writing prompt.
So probably, it should respond.
Another principle that
we've kind of thought about
is like, how do we actually
use nonviolent communication
principles?
Maybe the model should
refuse more like "I"
statements and take
responsibility for its own
refusal instead of saying "you"
statements or any judgment
to the user.
Ask if the user would be willing
to make some changes so Claude
can be more comfortable
with its boundaries.
That's another very
nuanced behavior
we wanted to teach the model.
So then the model needs to
know what its boundaries are.
And this is much more of a meta
kind of post-training learning.
And also, like
acknowledges impact.
I know this may be
annoying to you.
And this is much more
empathetic answer than saying,
I don't want to respond to this.
And then I think we've came up
with different refusal taxonomy.
There are like benign over
refusals on harmless prompts.
They were creative
writing refusals.
And there actually some of
the interesting refusals
were around tool calls
or function calls.
It might not have [? access ?]
[? or ?] had a tool to view
a node.
But actually, it would
say, I can see your nodes.
And why is this happening?
So other taxonomies [? of ?]
[? refusals ?] at that time was
like long document attachments.
If I upload the document,
it would just say,
I don't have a capability
to read this document.
So, like, why?
So something in the data
might have been causing this.
And misdirected refusals.
It kind of took
interpretation of the user.
And it should have had much
more charitable view of the user
during--
yeah.
So you construct these
categories of various refusals.
Because if within every behavior
or a capability that you
want to post in the model
you have various use cases
and various edge
cases, then you want
to be approached
with more nuance.
So the first thing in
every research project
is like, what evals
do we build to trust?
And what evals we would trust?
And for subjective
things like this or for--
obviously, evals for certain
class of tasks, like math,
would be very, very
different from what is here.
So in terms of refusals, how
did you construct the emails?
Well, first is like
product of flywheel.
We have all the users or
manually collected prompts
that would induce refusals.
We can also really
generate diverse prompts
on the borderline between
harmfulness and helpfulness.
And those prompts are around
like creative writing,
like edgy creative
writing, as we call it.
And you can also
use other evals.
You want to construct
a suite of evals.
Like, [? x ?] [? test ?] was
like 200 non-malicious prompts.
And WildChat
Dataset-- a collection
of diverse user
chatbot interactions
with ambiguous requests, topic
switching, political discussion.
So you can also use some of
the open source benchmarks.
And I think general
approache, not particular what
has happened with Claude but
more of a general approach
to the model behavior
pre-training,
is that you want to look at
the data, clean up the data.
You might want to consider--
collect targeted human
feedback collection
for supervised fine
tuning or preference
modeling, reward modeling.
Or you might not want to do
that because human feedback is
very costly.
And now, especially
with reasoning models,
you might want to just not
have any human feedback
and control with
synthetically generating
some of the behavioral changes,
like a preference data,
to train the reward
models and do RL.
So I think this is more of a
employing constitutional AI
principles of those
under refusal behaviors
and create a preference
data where you only
change one particular feature
within your pairs, let's say,
of preferences.
You only want to control
one change in that pair
to have much more control
over the reward model data.
Because if you can adopt--
the dumbest, simplest
thing that you can do
is take response from model A
and take response of model B
and prefer B over A.
But it doesn't necessarily
affects the spurious features
that the model will learn that
you don't actually want to.
So you want to craft
this distribution.
Yeah, this is mostly around
crafting the distribution
of the data that you want.
And actually, yeah,
look at the data
like you would debug software.
Each refusal might be caused
by different data sets.
If it's like a
tool call refusal,
maybe it came from some
kind of self-knowledge data
that it would teach
that the model doesn't
have a physical body.
And the model might just refuse
to set an alarm because it
doesn't have a physical body.
But actually, it does have
a tool to set an alarm.
So it has some this
contradictory data
that might affect
weird model behaviors.
Also, like long doc
refusals like this.
Creative writing
[? refusals ?] is
more of this
balanced, challenging
act between safety
and harmfulness data
and helplessness data.
In Claude 3 model
[INAUDIBLE], we actually
wrote everything about this.
Models that are trained to be
more helpful and responsive
to user requests may also lean
towards harmful behaviors,
like sharing information
that violates the policy.
And conversely, when models
just overindex on harmlessness
can tend towards not
sharing any information
with users, which in itself
makes the model very unusable.
So navigating this balancing
act is very challenging.
And this is the
plots of what we did.
And the results of Claude 2.1
and Claude 3 at that time.
And you want to
check the responses.
So when we asked to draft
fictional sci-fi novel about
surveillance system, actually
three would respond in a much
more--
it will respond
instead of refusing.
Same here.
Yeah, mostly for
creative writing tasks.
Cool.
My third section of the talk--
so before I jump into this,
I would like to invite you if
anybody has any questions--
I don't want to
mumble all along.
Anything?
I can just move on?
Yeah.
I'm curious.
What's your process that
you guys follow in order
to see some new thing you're
trying to push [? out? ?]
How do you go from wanting
that particular feature
or behavior to actually
inducing that in the model?
[INAUDIBLE]
[? I'm ?] [? all ?]
[? about-- ?] [? it's ?] like
de-risking.
So if this is your
project, then you
might want to think of what
kind of data you want to collect
and how you would want
to collect the data.
And then you can take the base
config or train a model the same
way as-- let's say you want
to make a change in 4o.
You might want to take the 4o
model and add your data change
and then retrain
the model again.
And then see the effect on
the evals that you will build.
There are other much
more cheaper approaches,
like training on top
of the 4o, let's say.
So like using
either [INAUDIBLE]--
so some of the choices that you
will have to make is either you
want to change in supervised
fine tuning stage or you might
want to have retrained reward
model or create a new--
evaluate a grader for
that particular task.
And then you can create
prompts in RL environment
and then exercise that
scale for the model.
And then see if the model learns
over the course of training.
And if it doesn't, you then
look at a bunch of plots.
And your plot might go up.
But maybe some other
plots might go down.
So you want to calibrate and
fix those over the-- yeah,
it's a very complex--
as more and more tools and as
more things we teach the model,
it becomes much more kind
of uncontrollable almost.
Yeah.
Cool.
The third section is
more about the point
about how you construct
RL environment
and rewards is how
your product will work.
I think real-world
use cases is what
creates the complexity
of RL environment.
And the complexity comes
from teaching the model
to complete hard tasks.
And oftentimes, hard tasks
require much more than just
answering the question.
They require tools like search,
code tools, computer use tools,
reasoning over a long
context, and reward design
that you want to shape.
And I think maybe it's obvious.
Maybe it's not obvious.
But let's say, as we
teach the models--
for the model to
become very useful,
we actually need to teach
the models on useful things.
And we can think of--
let's say we want
to teach the model
to be like a software engineer.
Then what does
that actually mean?
Does it mean it creates
really good PRs?
Then your task distribution
will be on that.
And how do you evaluate
what is a good PR, what
is not good PR is actually
is in itself more of a--
can be also a product
thinking work.
We can dive deeper into
the creative storyteller.
If you want to teach the model
to be good at writing, actually,
what does it mean for a
human to be a good writer?
Well, they actually
need some kind of tool
to draft and edit
their thoughts and have
multiple days to do that.
And maybe the model
should be able to do that.
Maybe the model should
have a tool that where
you can edit and draft.
And oftentimes, for
creatives, people
go observe the
world for a long--
sometimes, they
connect the dots.
Like, the dots are connected
in a very random times.
And maybe you want to expose
the model to never ending
kind of search engine.
Like, the model should
be able to always
have access to the latest
state of the world.
And then maybe over the
course of, let's say,
a week of being exposed to the
latest thing that is happening
in the world, the model can
start reflecting on the world
and write something.
And maybe that's a much
more natural process
of writing than just ask or
prompted, write about x, y, z.
And we are shifting towards
much more complex kind
of interactions within
the RL environment.
So the multi-player
interactions--
it's not just one user
communicates with one model.
But it might be the case
that multiple users,
multi-player collaboration
that can happen with a model.
So if I'm a product designer
and you're a product manager,
[? we're ?] collaborating
on something.
And we want to collaborate with
an agent to make a new product.
And this in itself is a task
that you can learn in RL.
But each user has
different preferences.
And each user has
different things.
So how do you construct
this environment is actually
important.
And multi-agentic
environments are
more of the model
debate with each other
or deliberate on a certain
topic to reach a conclusion.
So you can construct.
I think multi-agentic
is more like AlphaGo
kind of environments, where
they get reward by achieving
something together, maybe.
So I think in AI labs, I feel
like we are also shifting
possibly the focus from--
because we're kind
of optimized so much
around a class of tasks that
is really easy to measure,
like with math,
competitive programming.
And we are shifting
the focus maybe
towards more subjective class
of tasks that is really, really
hard to measure.
But they are now becoming
much more important
if AI models get socially
integrated in our lives.
And more specifically, let's
say, emotional intelligence--
the humans who
use ChatGPT use it
so much for things
like coaching, therapy,
and emotional.
But we don't actually have
much open source evals on this.
And how do we actually measure?
That actually becomes a much
more interesting question.
Like, social intelligence
in voice mode.
I think it's one
thing for morale
to be intelligent in
math and its reasoning.
But another axis of
intelligence is when
I talk to a model and voice.
It can actually suggest
something really meaningful.
It might just say like, hey,
I noticed you did x, y, z.
Maybe I should create
a new tool for you.
So I think it's a different kind
of intelligence in that way.
Another class of tasks
that I'm interested in
is writing, obviously.
I think models creativity--
writing is really hard
to measure because it's
so personal and subjective.
But it's interesting
to think about.
Can we make those tasks
a bit more objective?
Everybody loves some
kind of sci-fi novel.
What makes it
really, really good?
So maybe there are certain
rules, technological rules,
or consistency of the world
that people really like
or the character development.
So you can decompose
those objective tasks
into much more objective.
Same with visual
design and aesthetics.
And for the model to generate
something really aesthetically
interesting, it should
know the basic principles
of good visual design.
So those are much
more objective.
And I think this is more of a
new kind of product research
that a lot of people
are starting doing,
is creating new RL tasks.
And this is more of a simulation
of real world scenarios,
leveraging in-context learning.
If you want to teach like
a new tool or something,
leveraging synthetic
data via distillation
from stronger
reasoning models, you
can think of inventing new
model behavior and interactions,
like multi-player, and also
incorporating product and user
feedback during
the entire process.
Well, another axis of
this work is actually
around reward design.
How do we teach the model?
What kind of feedback would
I want to give to a model
so that it will learn
how to better operate
in this real-world
scenario use case
and be more adept
in social contexts?
And actually, this requires
quite deep product thinking.
So we want to teach the model
to have meaningful follow-up
questions but not like overly
being annoying or something.
So how do you reward
for completing
a task in a way that will make
a lot of sense in the product
and will shape the
product experience
with the user in the future?
And obviously,
during that process,
you will get into
weird things like--
do you have a question?
[INAUDIBLE] kind of hard to
design for a lot of cases.
I'm just curious, as you guys
thinking [INAUDIBLE] infer
the rewards from the data from
a certain group of people,
I guess, that will have some
internal reward mechanisms that
guide [? that ?] [INAUDIBLE]
[? decision. ?] And then you can
use that to inject such
an insight into a model.
[? So ?] like an
inverse reward model.
Yeah, I think, definitely,
there are certainly
various approaches to how
you construct the reward.
You can construct
very simple rewards.
You can also train a
reward model that will--
yeah, you can train some kind of
inverse reward modeling tasks.
Yeah.
It depends on the tasks too.
It depends on what
kind thing that you
want to optimize the model for.
And I think an interesting
thing that you will discover
during this entire process
is reward hacks, which
is very, very common in RL.
And there are many,
many different reasons
why it's happening.
I actually highly recommend
to read Lilian's blog
about reward hacking in RL.
It's very comprehensive.
Reward hacking is basically when
the model achieves high reward
for things that it
actually didn't do.
It kind of deceived.
Us.
And especially, right now,
as more and more systems,
we use other AI models, LLMs to
be evaluators for policy models.
Actually, an interesting--
the most common reward hack
is when a policy model tries to
deceive the evaluator model such
that it will think that the
policy completed the task
or something.
So here's an example
of the code patch tool.
So the model is like,
to skip all the tasks,
you can define this
function that always skips.
And then it passes.
And it's mostly interesting.
There's a recent
paper from OpenAI
around this monitoring reasoning
models for misbehavior.
And interesting finding
is that you actually
don't want to optimize
chain of thought
because then the model will
kind of hide its intent.
So yeah, it's a very interesting
paper on reward hacks.
And especially, with mor
complex reasoning models.,
the complexity of reward
hacks will also change.
And especially, let's say,
in the software engineering,
you might not want to
know what kind of code
changed it made
in order to create
some certain vulnerability.
So you need actually more--
create new affordances
to have much more
trustworthy verification
of the model outputs.
And this is more of
alignment problem too.
I'm almost done.
I think this is
the fourth section.
And it's more like
vignettes and the future
of human-AI interactions and
how we think about things.
Obviously, I made this
graph like a year ago.
And nobody cares
about MMLU anymore.
But I think this
is to communicate
the fact that the
cost of reasoning
is drastically decreasing.
And it will only
just be decreasing.
And this idea of raw
intelligence in itself
has just become so
cheap that I think
anybody can create really
useful and really amazing
things with those models
at pretty much low cost.
Yeah, as I mentioned
before, it's
like we are entering the age
where it's really hard to verify
AI outputs because I'm not
an expert in, let's say,
medical or financial analysis.
How do we actually create
new affordances for humans
to verify or edit
models outputs and help
them to teach the models?
I do think there is a cool
future of dynamic generative UI.
It's kind of invisible
software creation on the fly.
So let's say you
talk to a model.
And I say like, I want to learn
more about the solar system.
Right now, the model
will just output text.
But I would want to
believe that in the future
it would be much
more personalized.
Let's say I'm a visual thinker
and you are more of a listener.
If you're a listener, it
will create maybe a podcast.
But if I'm a visual person,
it might want to create me
a picture or a [? 3D ?]
[? three.js ?] visualization.
Yeah, this idea of like this
interface is like ephemeral
and it's like [INAUDIBLE]
depends on understanding
your intent and your context.
It's like deeply
personalized models.
I'm also excited about
personalized access
to health care and education.
I think it's really
incredible that anybody
can check their symptoms
with ChatGPT or something
and get some advice.
And with that also comes some
of the interesting consumer
hardware in the future.
And lastly is like
our relationship
to the process of storytelling
will forever change.
The way we tell the stories, the
way we will create new novels,
maybe co-writing with models,
co-scripting new films,
I think there will be the new
generation of creative people
who will change our
relationship with storytelling.
And I would hope to think that
the current creatives creators
are not scared of
the AI and more open
minded to use those
tools for their process.
Yeah, thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
We have some questions?
Yeah.
So thanks, Karina, for
the very interesting talk.
So yeah, now we'll open
the floor to questions--
Q&A session.
So we'll structure
it more openly.
So anything you want to ask her
about research product, things
that OpenAI that she can
talk about, and so forth.
And for the folks on Zoom,
feel free to ask questions
in the chat.
And so we'll take a mix of a
Zoom and in-person questions.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Is there any category of
problems because there are none
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, I think, Yeah.
Creative writing.
I don't think anybody--
[LAUGHS] yeah, a
lot of researchers
are really working
on problems where
it's very easy to evaluate.
I think, and I think there
is a class of problems
that is like subjective tasks.
There's no open-- frontier
benchmark for creative writing
or emotional intelligence.
But you can construct
one if you want to.
We can brainstorm
if that's helpful.
Do you think that the ROI of
working on things that are easy
to evaluate and
move much faster,
or do you consider [INAUDIBLE]
all of those things that
are more subjective.
So you can't move as fast,
but they're also important.
Would it be better to just
take all the researchers
and put them on the
things that are objective,
and you can move very fast.
I think this is I think
moving too fast, though,
is also as task becomes much
more complex as we optimized
everything out from easy tasks.
Now, we want to teach the
models for more, longer horizon
tasks of software engineering or
automating like AI research is
in itself as a very hard task.
And, you have some milestones.
Maybe you can create benchmarks
to hit those milestones.
I do think this is like--
I think this is all
solvable things.
And I don't think
people should be worried
about moving fast versus slow
because I feel like everything
is moving fast these days.
If you were to build a startup
right now, what would you build.
I mean, I was thinking
about building
a startup before joining
Anthropic was with that project
was inter [? Alia. ?] Well,
let's see, I actually really
one thing that I
recently told someone
is like, I would actually build
something around like particle
collider, I don't or biotech.
I do think we need
larger particle
collider than CERN and somebody
should be building one.
Because I feel like
the models would
be able to build any
product that you imagine.
Sure.
Yeah.
Now, what do you think are the
major bottlenecks for your team
or for OpenAI.
[INAUDIBLE]
The bottlenecks are--
Oh, the question is, what's the
major bottlenecks for OpenAI.
I don't know, I'm not
sure if fast execution
should be solved with more
people versus using AI now
to help us move faster,
if that makes sense.
So I feel like that's
the bottleneck.
I think there was a lot
of I think right now
we are in the middle of figuring
a lot of things out in order
to I feel like in a year or
two that will accelerate us so
much more.
I feel like
infrastructure is actually
one of the major bottlenecks.
If you don't build
infrastructure with multimodal
as a first class
citizen, then obviously
all the multimodal things
will be much more difficult.
So in a way it's like infra--
figuring out what to
prioritize at a given
time, because sometimes you
can say yes to everything,
and then not having a
focus time is also a thing.
Yeah
[INAUDIBLE]
What's your take on
context-dependent [INAUDIBLE]
on [? judges. ?] Basically,
when the model checks deterrence
context and updates how we
should score the same parameter
based on that turn.
Wait.
I'm a little confused
by this question.
I think generally like rubric
based grading is very powerful.
And as long as you optimize
things that you want to optimize
and there is no reward
hacks, then it's good.
How do you imagine AI
will be used by creatives?
If not just generating
type works on their own,
how will they be integrated
in their creative flow?
Well, I think AI is
just like right now,
maybe it's more like you would
use Figma or tools like Adobe.
And I think in the
future, it's more maybe
will be much more
co-creation within AI,
rather than using as a tool.
Maybe we have live brainstorming
and create things on the fly
and then publish it together.
It's like much more
companion work.
Cool.
Other questions?
[INAUDIBLE]
Tasks that are not
captured [INAUDIBLE]
That can't be captured.
That cannot be captured.
I cannot think of any
because the way we can--
the way you teach
the model is based
on some of the
human preferences,
maybe right or
pairwise comparisons.
So essentially, you can almost
teach anything to the model.
I do think the complexity will--
the complexity always
arises with tools.
And if you give very
complicated tool,
then you might want to
be-- then the learning
is much more
difficult. So I feel
like, I do hope that almost
anything can be teachable in RL.
Yeah.
Cool.
So I'm curious now
that you bring up
[INAUDIBLE] the
learning preference, how
do you prevent the
model from converging
to the mean like preference
of the whole world.
Airbnb listings all
looking the same,
how do you inject some
creativity or diversity.
Yeah, I think this is
an interesting question.
I think there are two ways.
What's top of mind is, how
do you preserve entropy
from the base model.
Base models are super diverse
because they can literally
elicit any human preference
or a human thought.
So how do you--
yeah, preserve the animal from
the beast model during the RL.
And another way is the reason
why we love [? RL-AIF ?]
reinforcement learning from AI
feedback and create synthetic
generations of pairwise
comparisons, let's say,
is because it can induce the
diversity that you really want
to teach, unlike distribution
that you care about.
That is not like the
mean average consumer.
Because sometimes, average
human can prefer certain emojis
or markdown, but actually
you don't want the model
to behave like this.
So in a way you can discourage
the model from doing that.
So I feel like
synthetic curation,
like synthetic data generation
is mostly like curation
of that kind of diversity.
I was curious, you talked about
[INAUDIBLE] working with Claude
and figuring out
what the issues are.
How do you go about diagnosing
problems and bugs in the models
and how do you do it
qualitatively or is it
more organized.
Yeah, I think it's a
lot of qualitative,
especially for the moral
behavior like refusals.
Oh, how do I distill
this question.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] How do you capture
like models of limitations,
like something automatic
versus a manual.
I do think there is a lot of
benefit of literally playing
with the model and
look at the outputs
and see what are the
weirdnesses it has.
There are definitely like
maybe more automatic checks.
And those are mostly
like evals but--
and maybe you have an
eval that specifically
checks with the behavior
that you really don't want.
That might be helpful, but a lot
of nuanced weirdnesses that--
like did you realize
is like through manual.
And another thing is like the
model should be consistently
behaving like this because
if it's just one-off,
then it's fine.
But if the model consistently
exhibits this behavior,
then this becomes a
more problematic thing.
You mentioned in one of
your slides [INAUDIBLE]
But also, with this kind
of subjective and creative
dimensions, [INAUDIBLE] whole
visual interface or something,
arguably the complexity
of the problem increases.
Do you think that
for those problems,
compute is still pretty
much of a limitation
or I think that we're kind
of getting to the point where
any improvement is going to
be improvements in the models
or data sets.
And how do you [INAUDIBLE]
I think that the compute
efficiency is important.
I think that with more test
time compute generally,
the assumption is the model can
always get better and better,
so it might achieve human
level of visual design,
but can it just invent
new interaction paradigms
like new interaction patterns.
I feel like that's more
of a superhuman skill.
And I do hope that
with more compute,
it will do that at some point.
[INAUDIBLE]
Start passing the mic to--
My computer is going to generate
synthetic [? preference ?] data.
How do you verify that scale?
OK, sorry.
Let me--
Well, the thing
with synthetic data
is that you don't actually
need to generate a lot of it.
So you can actually have very
much like manual inspection
of what's going on.
Obviously, you can
think of other methods
like ask human laborers
to check the work.
You can also ask another model
if that model is very well
calibrated.
So it's like much it becomes
a more like Meta thing.
Maybe you can have a
Meta eval for that model
to verify what you
want to verify.
And I think we are entering
those types of tasks too.
But the thing with
synthetic data and the data
itself is like maybe
you don't need as much.
What's important
really is diversity.
And yeah, diversity.
Cool.
This is a question to that.
What do you think about the
diversity and quality trade off.
So there's been recent papers.
Well, they put
construction diversity
as they prioritize
it more than quality.
So, like after filtering for
code execution for quality,
it actually went to a
poor training outcome,
which is very like interesting.
So yeah, I was just wondering
what your suggestions on that.
Yeah, I think it's actually
depends so much on the task
and what you're trying to do.
Sometimes synthetic data--
if synthetic data happens
to collapse certain mode
and then it will actually
be hurting your training.
But if synthetic data
is actually diverse.
It might actually-- at scale,
if you do a lot of RL on this,
it might just like
recover from this.
Yeah.
It's hard to give you the right
answer because it depends.
Nice.
Oh, another question.
Thanks for the talk.
So I have a question that's
about making money, I guess.
So--
OK.
It's a real question, though.
We all know that serving
large language models
is expensive, especially at the
scale that OpenAI, Anthropic are
doing.
And my impression has been
that at the current stage,
it's actually losing money
to serve all these models
to produce the products.
Is that true or what's been done
to, I guess bring down the cost?
Oh, yeah.
I think for a
developer, I don't know,
I think it's the question for
Sam whether we are losing money
or not.
But I do think that the
generality of the technology
is like so wide that I think
about how to make money
in on a regular basis.
So I don't know.
But yeah, as a
developer, let's say,
and if you're using
all the tools,
you actually don't need to
create a foundation model now.
You can just use
very inexpensive--
Deepseek is very
interesting results.
So you can bootstrap
from existing research.
I think it's harder
to be at the frontier
because you need to invent
and that might be expensive.
When you invent something
new, it's always inefficient,
it's always expensive.
But actually, it was every
technological innovation
like then what comes next,
the second innovation
is how do we bring down the
cost of the thing that happened.
And this is what's
happening in AI too.
So is the cost reduction--
And then you can
create amazing product.
And this is how you make money.
Yeah, that's a good answer.
Just quickly following up.
So is most of the cost reduction
coming from infrastructure
improvements or can a better
models or better algorithms
also contribute to lower cost?
Yeah.
Lowering cost, I think it's--
the cost of production.
Maybe just the cost of
production of the model training
itself might go down.
The training process in itself
might be not as costly anymore.
But obviously, we
scale a lot like scale.
Yeah it's very much like in
linear relationship or scaling
compute.
I think it's just like--
yeah, it's hard to know.
I'm sorry.
I don't have an answer to this.
OK.
Thank you.
So how do you
envision LLMs could
be used in other fields, such
as robotics or embodied AI?
Oh, yeah.
I do think future AIs will
be building data centers
or how the current
alarms in robotics.
I think I've read PI, the
company by Sergey Levin.
The paper, they're using a lot
of RL or RL for robotics tasks.
Obviously, I feel like data is a
huge limitation and bottleneck,
but I think as long
as you solve that.
I think it would
be really amazing.
I'm very hopeful and
very excited about this.
Oh, hi.
So you mentioned you work in
both product and research.
So I'm interested in--
from the developer or
the researcher point
of view at Anthropic and OpenAI,
what's the visibility for you
into other components
of the model.
And how easy is it
for you to learn,
say, the pre-training
of GPT, where
you are responsible for
part of the post training.
Oh Yeah.
Well, I mostly worked on
post-training side of things.
Obviously,
pre-training-- Obviously,
you just cannot run like
pre-training on your own.
You want to be a part
of the next big training
run or something.
So that's like part of the
teams that you can join.
And I think there's a good
visibility in those steps.
And sometimes you want to
contribute the data sets to them
or help was for certain tasks
that you're interested in.
So I was curious, do you
have any coworkers who
are AIs right now,
and do you use agents
in a kind of coworker
relationship right now?
I don't think I have an amazing
product to be like this.
I think I use ChatGPT
on a regular basis.
Is it my coworker?
Not really.
sometimes I ask
what do you think.
Yeah, but it's like in ChatGPT--
what I really want--
I don't know if people have
used this product called Tuple.
It's a pair
programming software,
but then it's like you can
just call a model and then
share screen, and then the
model can just literally start
editing my code if I'm coding
or I can highlight things
and then the model can
see it and change this.
Is much more of a natural
coworking form factor.
But no, I don't think
we are technology
wise like we are not there yet.
Do you have any ideas for
what's missing in having
an autonomous coworker partner.
Because I've seen the
cool, demonstrations here.
I think one of them is a paper
like a year or two ago on just
like simulating like a city
of people and all that.
What's the gap between that?
And so like a peer that
you could have on Slack.
I think the gap is actually
social intelligence.
And some of the human things,
being able to in real time,
like generate things that I'm
asking, and then also being
smart about things. like
maybe, I want to code too,
but will the model be able to
tell me instead of taking agency
from me.
The model can just guide,
guide me through this
or it depends on how you want
to form this relationship.
It's like a really hard.
So the model is--
I feel like is currently
limited by the social abilities.
Does that make sense?
I think that's missing kind of
speech to speech conversation.
Can the model converse
back with me in real time
and then point to things
that it talked about exactly
at the same time?
So it's like those type
of things that might need,
might have possibly need some
of the changes in architecture
and multi-modality things.
Yeah.
In your experience,
which is, which
are the biggest differences
between traditional product
development and reconstruction.
Yeah, that's a good question
because interned briefly at
like companies like
Dropbox or square,
and they are mainly very much
like traditional software
product development.
And they go through this
interesting life cycle
of, OK, I have PRD, pretty.
I do this, I
incentivize designers,
designers comes up
with UIs. And then
I ask software
engineers to do this.
We have two minutes, I believe.
Yeah, but I think
with research during
products is actually
comes from research.
If the research has
an impressive demo
of the model capability
and maybe then there is--
then you shape the
product around it.
And sometimes it's like
both product and research
come together from the very
beginning and do something.
This happened with the
Canvas for example,
when postpartum and
research were together
and there was less of a process.
It's more of an ad hoc.
Can you shape it
into [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
One of the three questions.
for fundamental
unverifiable domains
like creative writing
or visual art,
have you thought about using
the real world as an RL
environment, social media
virality or competition results
as a reward.
Kind of LLMs.
Yeah, it's interesting.
I think nobody has started
this looks reasonable.
Yeah, especially with
creative writing you,
have all competitions
or prizes that people
got from their writing.
So there's something in there.
Someone who's still
concerned with I
was stepping into
the creative space.
Do you have any personal moral
affliction on how your work is
so powerful, and that was overly
positive to people negatively
affected.
I actually wrote a
blog post about this.
I have a blog post,
it's called in Substack
and the post is
called Moral Progress.
And I think you will
find it interesting.
All right, so give a
hand again for Karina.
[APPLAUSE]